this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SC Radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software hello everyone this is Felina
for se radio my guest today with me is
andre aesthetic and very suffolk is an
associate professor in computer science
at the University of Nevada at Las Vegas
Andreas has been working on creating
technologies that make it easier for
people including those with disabilities
to write computer software he helped
establish the first national educational
infrastructure for blind or visually
impaired students to learn computer
science and he is also the inventor of
quorum the first evidence oriented
programming language in 2016 andreas
received the White House Champions of
Change Award in computer science
education
welcome to the show under yes thank so
thanks for inviting me so this show is
about how blind and visually impaired
people interact with software but first
let's start with the basics how many
blind or visually impaired people are
there in the world what should we take
into account when designing software for
them
it's about 1.3 million people ballpark
and
in the US and that's a lot of people
it's enough to at least make a dent on
any kind of mark-to-market you could
sell for so help us understand how blind
people use in computer because most
people that listen to the show probably
are sighted sighted is how we call
people like that can see and they are
used to using the mouse looking at the
screen what do blind or visually
visually impaired people do there's a
variety of things that they do many
people that are blind or visually
impaired have partial vision or
sometimes called functional vision
depending on what it is and usually that
means they can see some things or they
can see color or they can see some
amount of light depending upon the
person so in those cases you might use
technologies like screen magnifiers or
you might use literally a magnifying
glass or other types of things if you
are non sighted meaning you have no
sight at all or you have no know
that's effectively functional then a
more typical device is either Braille or
a screen reader probably the most common
is screen reader technologies and
basically what it means is that the
computer translates what's on the screen
into speech can you give us an
impression for how that would look like
so if if a screen reader listens to or
loops at the webpage how does that sound
slash Luke yeah I'll turn it on your
2016 web content you are currently on
web content do you enter the wet area
press ctrl option shift down arrow that
particular screen reader is called
voiceover it's the screen reading option
that happens to be on Mac on Windows
there's a bunch of them there's one
called
NVDA which is free there's one that's
made by a company called Freedom
Scientific called jaws it's pretty
popular but quite quite expensive and
Windows has one built in as well that's
been improving over the last few years
so when we listen to it it's not only
reading the text on the website it can
also navigate the website and give us
information on where you are it said
something like you are now at yeah
that's good so there's a funny thing so
academics often talk about this with a
certain term they call it the we're at
my problem I think the person that
defined that was a woman by the name of
excuse me Joan Fran Fran Sione or
Frankie and I'm not sure I've never met
her actually but in any case the idea is
pretty simple it's that the screen
reader ties to give you both a sense of
the content and a sense of like where
you are on the page like the semantics
of a web page like I'm in a heading or
I'm in a paragraph or I want a level 2
heading stuff like that yeah because not
only consuming the text is a problem
navigating is also a big problem I found
there stupid right yeah that's bad yes
the navigation parts of it are probably
the most crucial because think about it
like this if I gave you a long website
and I just read the text linearly it
would be pretty hard to understand
because it might be very long and if you
can navigate a web page then you can
selectively determine what information
to understand when and that makes it a
lot easier so so far we've talked about
sites and navigation but the four stars
also apps and programs do they also work
way to build in screen reader or new app
and program developers have to do
something special
it's complicated unfortunately so on the
web's on the web there's a number of
rather excellent standards for
accessibility in part just because the
web's used a lot so to give your
listeners an example one is called Aria
Aria is basically a way that you can do
interactive websites it's sort of the
type of thing if you wanted like an
interactive Facebook or something to be
blind accessible apps can definitely be
accessible as well but how they're
accessible varies by platform and is
actually one of the sort of pain points
for example if I want to make my app
from Apple accessible there's certain
Apple II type things that I have to do
and they're kind of tricky and Android
has its own platform with its own
language is an ecosystem on top of that
if you're using apps on something like a
tablet or phone they have different
screen reader technologies so Apple has
voice over which I think most people
credit a scholar named Shawn cane for
inventing sort of like really cool
gestures that you use specifically for
blind individuals and Android sort of
has those too but they kind of have
weird variations and are complicated can
we talk a little bit more about
voiceover on the iPhone because I've
seen in an action but I think our
audience might be a little bit confused
how does that work with because the only
interface is the screen and the icons
how does that work and how does it work
with the special gestures okay so how to
describe it in words okay so um think
about it like this like if I want to if
I'm a sighted user and I'm scrolling
wrong along I might move my finger up
and down and that would let me see the
content but if I'm blind oftentimes what
I do is I might tap or tap on parts of
the screen or DoubleTap to interact with
it and when I do that if I hit a target
it'll talk so the idea is that I can use
gestures to sort of interact
semantically with the tablet as opposed
to just scrolling with a finger and
reading it
so it would read for example the name of
the apps and then if I hear the app I
once I would tap and then it would open
that app yeah stuff like that so like my
friend a friend of mine that does Ober
all the time on his iPhone taps it in a
certain way and that'll give him a sense
of where it is on the map and things
like that
so you can actually use a lot of apps so
long as the developer codes it in yeah
so let's talk about that as long as the
developer codes it in a little bit so
how well are we doing at this point are
most apps operating systems and websites
accessible
are they notes are they medium
accessible how well are we doing I don't
think I could give you a number in terms
of a percentage but a feeling for you
yeah I would say that there are some
companies that do a really great job and
that those are often somewhat bigger
ones but that we have a really long way
to go and that's not a criticism it's
just an observation I mean oftentimes
developers don't actually get any
training on building these in school and
it's not trivial so it's not like it's
not like we have a long way to go
because the technologies are all bad for
some reason it's just that we usually
don't even teach this in school you know
a developer doesn't learn about the NS
accessible libraries on Mac which are
the common thing or if you're on desktop
platforms Microsoft has its own
libraries and Apple has its own
libraries and Linux has its own
libraries and all of them are different
and none of them are compatible so
personally I think that it would be a
lot easier for developers to develop
accessible technology if there was like
a unifying standard across platforms but
that doesn't really exist at this stage
of the game at least yeah that was
actually one of my goals in inviting you
for an episode is to make developers
more aware and to help them what they
can do to make their so far more
accessible which was also my next
question okay what can we do as
developers what are the things we need
to think about when wanting to make our
apps more accessible okay so the the
first thing to do if you design a
website is that there's a special set of
guidelines from the w3c and they are
specifically for accessibility
don't make sure we'll link to those in
the show notes so people can check them
out
yeah and though those are affected
easily the most comprehensive source
about how to make a website accessible
and they're great they just tell you
like if you have a link how you make
that accessible what kind of if you have
a picture and obviously you can't see it
you put in some kind of alt text right
and there's there's all sorts of small
things that you can do there's also some
online accessibility checkers that you
can use nice and they're not perfect you
know they can't tell you that your
website is easy to use but sometimes
they can at least give you like a check
and balance or some of the easy thing
like hey you forgot your alt text for
that image you should go fix that stuff
like that yeah what are some of the
issues so all text is I think something
people are familiar with even if they
don't always use it you mentioned links
what are best practices for links that
are easy to fix okay so with links one
thing that is generally good is to not
give your link a moniker that doesn't
have semantic meaning so for example um
to do this go here the word here should
not be a link because then when you get
it through the the screen root is gonna
stop it's gonna say link here and you're
gonna say where's here so what would be
better is to say go to the website for
the bla and have that whole part be a
link it sounds like a minor thing but in
a screen reader can make a difference
cuz you have to listen to it yeah that
is relatively easy to fix because super
so let me understand how exactly that
we're the screen reader if you're
navigating there would be an option to
go through all the links and if they
were all labeled here it will be here
here here
whereas if you would say the website of
Andreas or a website of University of
Nevada as a link you could more easily
navigate yeah that's the kind of idea
like anytime that you have a structure
give it a semantic meaning that's
exactly right
yeah any other things that are
relatively easy to fix that we should
think yeah so another one that is kind
of an obvious one I'll tell you one
that's sort of adorable my daughter is
like five and her school does a great
job but they have a couple accessibility
flaws on their website that are at just
make made me laugh a little bit like
they didn't do it intentionally it's
okay and so one thing that they did that
that just I thought was funny is they
but a schedule on line so what they did
is they took a picture of the schedule
like a complicated spreadsheet and then
they put that onto the website and then
it shrunk so if you're visually impaired
you can't actually read it because the
text is too blotted out and if you have
a screen reader you're gonna get to that
thing and it's gonna say image so you
can't actually do anything so one thing
to do is don't like replace content with
already accessible things you know if
you need to have a table put a table in
there and then give it the the markup
that it needs from the w3c yeah so
images should be for making your website
nicer but they shouldn't be replacing
content exactly also have been
represented sexually that's correct that
is actual advice so what about a user
interface if we're not no longer talking
about a website but something that has
buttons and drop-down menus scroll bars
why do we do with those so that's a
little bit trickier because it depends
on the platform and it also depends on
the API that you're using so for example
if you're using Java unfortunately while
Java technically has an accessibility
architecture a lot of it doesn't really
work that well or in some cases really
at all so this is unfortunate not
because you know it just is but because
if you're a developer you might be
thinking all right I'm gonna code to the
accessibility interface it's gonna be
awesome I'm gonna make this totally
accessible and then you turn it on on a
particular platform and you're like oh
it doesn't work and you can verify that
by turning on a screen reader which are
free oftentimes and so you just flip it
on and say oh it doesn't make sound I'll
give you an example in the NetBeans
development environment second tool for
programmers the text editor didn't work
for years so it's like the fundamental
thing like about how to use a
development environment like writing
text it was not accessible what was
wrong with it Java's accessibility
system doesn't work Wow and it's you
know it is what it is and there are
other there are other types of
environments that are much more
accessible so for example Microsoft for
whatever reason gets flack a lot but for
accessibility they've done a pretty dang
good job right they they're api's work
pretty well they're not perfect but
they're well thought through
many years and they're compatible with a
lot of systems it's not a plug for
Microsoft I have no vested interest but
they have this thing called I accessible
to and basically a few code to I
accessible to then your stuff is almost
certain to be accessible but if you're
working at sort of a higher level then
sort of the low level old comm type
stuff and you're just using sheets
c-sharp they've done a pretty dang good
job of like building it in so that
buttons and text boxes and stuff like
that are mostly accessible nice so if
you stick with developer tools from
baked platforms you usually there are
okay well it depends on the platform job
is pretty big - but it's debatable
whether it's accessible depending on
platform where a c-sharp is at least
pretty dang accessible on Windows in
terms of a Mac they do have something
called NS accessible and that does work
pretty well if you're only writing in
the Mac ecosystem the tricky thing is
whenever you're using other programming
languages in those ecosystems like for
example is small talk accessible is
Python accessible it's it's County you
have to take it on a case-by-case basis
because of the platform
yeah that's see of those tools but - on
Windows is different from bites on a Mac
a kandi okay it depends on like what the
devs implemented so so there still some
- some things that we need to know about
as developers because the platforms
aren't going to take care of it
yeah in fact this is one reason why I've
cared about the consistency of
programming languages in part is because
it impacts some groups pretty poorly
like the blind you know like I'll give
you an example
our tools for the blind I think are
written in like eight programming
languages and we don't want them to be
but we have to connect to these
different systems there's really no
choice something like that six day and I
forget mm-hmm so what about other things
that we should take care of so one of
the things that has surprised me a lot
in working with like children only a
little bit is that some stuff like
working with the mouse takes lots of
energy if you're really impaired but not
entirely blind so you can see a little
bit so we we started people who think oh
you can use the mouse
but tracing where the mouse cursor is
and using the mouse takes lots of energy
that was this thing that surprised me a
lot are there a few other things that we
like this that we should think about
yeah and actually there's some stuff
that GUI to GUI toolkit designers can do
that are pretty easy so for example if
you're designing some kind of a text box
type interface and it doesn't be text
box but something that where you would
follow a pointer
whenever the pointer moves if someone is
magnified follow it right so that that
if you're moving a magnification system
they always have the context of where
the most important thing is I'm sort of
fool the focus should follow the cursor
yes okay yeah so like if you're like for
example one of my old students I
shouldn't say his name since you know
because he happens to be blind right and
he used a magnifier pretty heavily and
when he would use just typical GUI
elements for example imagine if you
pressed a button and open the menu but
it didn't jump to that menu and you're
highly magnified it's a lot easier if
the magnification system follows you but
not all the upper systems do that oh and
then you'd have to scroll which is super
hard yes magnify yeah so I click the
menu and then you have to like tap the
mouse a bunch to sort of get it up there
and hope that you can find it and it
gets tricky so focus is a big issue
focus is a huge issue in any order huge
issues like that let's see so for in
terms of trying to make general user
interfaces accessible one that my team
has been working on that I think is
really fun is we've been trying to
figure out how to make graphics
accessible so here's the tricky part if
you've got something like like let's
just say unity 3d which is sort of like
this game design platform right we have
a grant from the National Science
Foundation right now to try to take big
complicated 3d interfaces like that and
make them blind accessible but here's
the road well you can make buttons and
stuff like that accessible there's just
no way you can tell OpenGL make yourself
blind accessible there just is no
toolkit it is inherent
visual it is inherently a visual accept
any kind of 3d application still has
things you could potentially tell us
screen reader about so for example if
I'm navigating terrain or something like
that are trying to adjust terrain or a
3d model hypothetically you could
provide a list of things that could be
positions on that terrain and tell it to
go up and down which would still give a
screen reader information so one of the
things we're trying to invent in the lab
is a way for blind children to be able
to write their own 3d computer games and
be able to adjust it through their
typical screen reading device without
needing any special stuff while still
having it be hardware accelerated and
all that stuff it's been a hard project
that's taken me four years to get a
handle around in my brain but I think
we're getting pretty close and are those
things that also usable for let's say
more practical things that are
inherently visual I'm thinking of a
diagram or a map or a graph see that's
the thing if you can do that for the
hard stuff in graphics any of the rest
comes comes easily yeah Fernan oh yeah
we talked about frameworks and libraries
already a little bit so you mentioned NS
accessible that's a framework that we
can use to make stuff more accessible
sort of out of the box are there other
things we should check out frameworks of
libraries
yeah the big ones the big the two
biggest ones are NS accessible on Mac
and I accessible two on Windows but I
think since in terms of the web by far
the two things that people should know
about are the w3c accessibility
standards and also this thing called
Aria this mildly motley hard to Google
sometimes you might have to say a RI a
space accessibility but the idea is that
the w3c standards sort of tell you any
pretty much anything you would need to
know about basic like content and the
Aria standards are really good at trying
to help you understand like interactive
content cool or auto-update Ajax stuff
things like that we'll make sure we add
all of that to the show notes so people
that want to know more can check it out
really cool so so far we've mainly
talked about tools everyday tools that
many people use like a website or an
or from but there's also people that
program while blinds and we as
developers might make tools for people
that want a program also more accessible
so I want to talk about that a little
bit how do blind people program and what
should we know about blind developers to
make developer tools more accessible yes
so actually blind developers fall into
the same categories so either visually
impaired or totally blind and they do
amazingly interesting things so for
example a number of blind developers
that design technologies for all sorts
of things one of my good friends
his name is Sina Brahm he designs
accessibility installations for museums
he won this award from the White House a
bunch of years back and got connected
with museums all over the world to build
like weird accessible interfaces and
stuff like that if you go to your museum
and there's an accessible thing it's
very likely he's been involved in some
capacity or another so what are we
thinking about accessible museums then
someone that's subscribing the painting
I could be all sorts of stuff and to be
honest I'm not exactly sure all the
details of what he does but I've seen
like some stuff here and there it seems
pretty cool but the point is as the
point isn't so much the details of what
he does it's how he does it
so how does he do it so what he does is
he uses his screen reader and then he
listens to the text now there's some
obvious complexity there so for example
if you to a sighted user sometimes as
developers we don't really think about
the sort of weird wacky syntax that
happens but as a blind developer you
literally have to listen to for left
paren data equals zero semicolon I less
than 10 semicolon I less I plus plus
right friend left brace or stuff like
that so a screen reader that's normally
used for text is then used in source
code and it just reads old symbols yeah
and it's not like you can't get used to
it but the problem is it depends you
know a lot on like where you are in the
development pipeline like if you're an
experienced professional you've already
made it past all the barriers and you're
good to go then yeah you're gonna be
fine but we've also spent a lot of time
talking to blind children and let's just
say the first time that a blind child
hears for left fernanda equals zero
semicolon i with some sense I would call
a 9 + + right paren left brace it's a
little weird and it sort of makes you
wonder why languages
built that way fair enough so for the
let's say end-user tools we talked about
navigation being a huge issue I can
imagine that is for programming as well
I think if I recode in an unfamiliar
codebase
I would scroll up enough to see what are
the classes what are the methods how
does the screen reader for blind people
navigate the source code because does it
have Hatter's does it take the cool text
into account where you could skip from
the one class to the other um yes and no
so it does but in the same way you know
when you're using a development tool
oftentimes you might have little like
navigators off to the side and it'll
have the list of the classes and method
so you can click on them oh yeah
oftentimes those are accessible so you
can still jump around however that
doesn't mean it's easy so when you're
one I think one of the harder things for
blind individuals is that you can
navigate a little bit and there's a
number of research teams that are
working on making those navigators
better but the one of the tricky parts
is you if you've got like a long method
getting context can be difficult so you
know 20 lines of really complicated code
you have to kind of memorize it to
figure out what's going on depending
upon what you're doing oh so you're
saying if you want to comprehensive
maybe you online you read another line
but you need to remember all of those
whereas if you're sighted the fanta
prior you could skip that until maybe
the loop that's in the methods and like
oh it loops over all the customers or
whatever it does yeah exactly so like if
I'm looking at a screen of code I can
kind of glance up and down to get very
quick context that's a little bit harder
if you're blind alright I guess many of
my blind friends would probably say that
it's not really harder but maybe slower
yeah or different different yeah Artur
things we can do as developers in that
respect what can we do to make developer
tools more accessible for example that
navigation can we make resource code
more easily navigatable for source code
it's tough I think that the bigger
issues are number one many of the
development ideas aren't very accessible
or if they are accessible they sort of
break every other release
it's again it's not like it's malicious
or anything it's just people don't think
about it so for example Visual Studio is
sort of accessible right now but
historically it's sort of you know is
sort of accessible sort of not depending
on the release or even if it is
accessible for certain I des sometimes
they make rather adorable decisions so
for example I remember a boy I forget
which version of visual studio it was
but I recall there was a little debugger
label and I had an arrow on it and so if
you're a blind person or like let's say
a child instead of giving you
information about what you're doing in
the debugger would say like graphic 53
and it's like I get it you can learn
that but it's sort of weird you have to
write so is that what you mean with sort
of accessible can you explain a little
bit in more more detail what what does
it mean if something is sort of
assessable is sort of what is it in what
parts is it accessible and what parts
isn't it I'm trying to think how to
describe this like have you ever been on
a website and like you could use it but
it sort of bothered you yeah it doesn't
feel logical right like the links are on
weird places and it looks strange and
stuff like that
that's true for accessible interfaces as
well so example if your page wasn't
structured with proper formatting then
you wouldn't be able to navigate it so
you might go to like go up and down with
a bunch of giant paragraphs but you
would definitely be annoyed and with IDs
it's kind of a similar situation it's
sort of like you might be able to
navigate the source code editor but
maybe the navigation doesn't work maybe
certain features are broken maybe you'll
get to certain windows and you can't
navigate through them or the Preferences
window won't be accessible but the other
windows are maybe the file save dialog
is broken so that this is the thing is
that a lot of these IDs is not so much
that they're good or bad as a whole
oftentimes they're just weirdly
inconsistent so certain interfaces will
be broken for a release or two and it
makes it kind of hard especially if
you're a learner but for professionals -
yeah I can imagine
oh inconsistency is bad for any
demographic yeah pretty much and I think
it's easy for a dev to accidentally
screw it up because they don't do it
everyone
there I think a lot of IDE designers
they don't usually test with a screen
reader and so they don't really notice
when something is broken for the blind
yeah going to that point what are things
we can do if we are in the field of
making ideas you're making IDE plug-ins
one thing we can do is test it with a
screen reader
do you have other concrete tips suppose
we're in the business of developing IDs
or related tools that are for
programmers why do we need to check so
there's a few things number one is if
you're at a big company and you have the
cash you can get a consultant to help
because it is tricky and so don't assume
that like you have to figure it all out
yourself there's lots of people out
there that know how to do it and that
can help with it
especially on the web the web is not
perfect nowadays but it's so much better
today than it was you know 20 years ago
or whatever and so that's number one
number two even though definitely
turning on a screen reader is a good
thing and can help figure stuff out the
the one tricky thing to do is to check
it compared to a variety of disabilities
so think that one thing to do is just
kind of go through a checklist of what
those could be so for example if you are
totally blind you might use a screen
reader but if you're visually impaired
which is a lot more people then you
might think of issues like color
contrast and those are online there's
online checkers for that and it's really
easy to do and even if you're not blind
that's helpful there too cuz like then
color contrast helps people read your
page you people could be color blind
they could benefit they can also be
colored by them but they could also just
like it makes it easier to read like for
example you know if you have black text
on white background that's really easy
to read but black text on dark grey
background maybe not so much and so a
lot of the issues that you do with
accessibility they tend to have these
other little benefits like your site is
generally easier reading so so that are
the top tips get it consultants help if
you can pay for it or use your own app
or website or IDE with a screen reader
enabled just to see how it feels
screenreader enabled but also don't
forget that the visually impaired
community is larger than the totally
blind commute
sure so think about things like
magnification color contrasts and stuff
like that yeah we haven't really talked
about the Braille interface in Lords oh
yeah actually it sounds weird but
actually a lot of the blind community
doesn't actually know Braille that's
that is surprising yeah it's sort of a
bizarre quirk but think about it like
this if you're blind and you go blind
later in life the question is do I just
turn on a screen reader which I can
download at no cost or do I buy a trail
to speed for like three to ten thousand
dollars and have to learn Braille right
so it's kind of a barrier however if
you're at if you're a young person and
you know blind for birth or very young
oftentimes it's a good idea to learn
Braille skills because it's a nice way
to read I'm so far as I understand it
but for us as developers the Braille
interface is not as big of a chunk of
the people we can reach as is optimized
for screen reader that's true and if
it's if your interface is accessible you
most of the time get the railing side
for free now there is some tricky stuff
like for example Braille standards
change over time and computer symbols in
Braille like that they use in
programming language languages don't
always come out well so there's really
I'm not exactly sure which ones I I have
a friend that's a Braille expert and I'm
that's not it sounds like you would know
about all these things but a lot of
these are really complicated and Braille
is one of those areas I know less about
but yeah little weird symbols that we
often use in programming languages for
whatever reason so so far we talked
about tools apps websites ie
one thing is really important to
developers that we have covered is the
command line does this creative work on
the command line what does it read is
that a better interface for people that
are visually impaired then running it
from an ITU for example um I say I
wouldn't say it's better but it's
definitely most of the time they're
accessible so a command-line interface
is definitely a nice fallback but when
you think about it oftentimes when
you're programming a command-line
interface is okay but I des offer you
all sorts of stuff like Auto refactoring
and all that fit all that so sometimes
it is nice to be able to use an IDE
which is why you know people I think
prefer it however a command-line
interface is almost always accessible
which is why it's not a bad option if
you have to okay so it's a good idea to
have a command interface come online
interface because it's sort of
accessible by default yeah you're
probably gonna have accessibility
support if you use one you know so you
briefly touched upon refactoring support
as one of the things that an IDE offers
us sighted people are those features
that blind people can use because if I
if I think of a refactoring IDE I think
of many things that are visual I let's
say the rename refactoring
I think of selecting a variable I think
of right clicking getting a context menu
selecting rename refactoring getting a
pop-up that says what's the new name
getting a preview of how my source code
would look like in a new version it's
like visual visual visual visual yeah it
sounds like it wouldn't be but they
usually are yeah yeah and the route has
to be but they usually are yeah and the
reason is because they know most of the
time they use normal GUI elements like
context menus and stuff like you're
saying and most of the time if you
program it correctly and like Java isn't
broken for accessibility then yes
they're accessible but I should say I'm
not trying to pick on Java it just
happens to be not accessible if that's
the way it is the weenus I was also
thinking about testing which also is
often inherently visual in the sense
that of failing tests would get thought
yeah exactly just do screen readers read
those thoughts I'm not sure about this
specific interface for like j-unit or
something but generally speaking those
things can be coded to be accessible and
also you can just dump it to the command
line and then it'll be accessible to you
far enough
and what about squigglies okay that's
tricky so there are a few things in
interfaces that are highly visual they
aren't super accessible so little
squigglies actually are believe it or
not or at least you can make them and
there's a couple ways you can do it one
is what we do in some of our tools for
the mind when you have a squiggly at the
very very like 0.1 seconds will go like
something like that so that way the
thing is is that you need it to be right
at the beginning of the line cuz you're
gonna browse you'll be like going up and
down between variables like this line
this
and then you can hear right away that
there's an error on the line so then in
that case you might you can either query
for the error you can check your compile
box or you can wait to the end of the
line and we embed it at the end of a
line so then it would be different from
how sighted people would perceive it
because for us the squiggly sometimes is
not in there the entire line but ended
up in the depart of the line that is the
issue oh yeah narrative would be
slightly different because you'd get the
error at the beginning of the line so
it's a bit less I think that's right for
me yeah but that's ok cool so all these
things that we perceive as visual are
understandable for blind users really
sometimes I mean there are tricky ones I
was just thinking of one so have you
ever used one of those like interfaces
for dips that are highly visual dips
oh yeah well you get like red is just
lines and green is the same lines
compared to the previous commit or to
master or something yeah it would be
awesome if those were accessible but I'm
not totally sure how to do it because
they're really really visual and they
often use non-standard components so
like custom little drawing tools and
things like that so I think it's
probably possible I've just never tried
yeah you in theory you could have
something similar where you have the
clicks at the beginning of the line for
what is red and green for one that's the
same
yeah and blind people definitely can and
do use version control so for example I
know we used to have a number of blind
children doing Lego robot competitions
and so they would use if I recall
correctly they'd use git to send files
back and forth to each other because the
command lines accessible and we make it
accessible and some of our up little IDs
to you just we just could never get like
visual diffing working this thing is a
hard problem in general even for people
that can see it kind of is and even if
you get it on the command line all those
weird little git symbols yeah those are
unreadable by anybody yeah they're
immutable for me using me too I want to
talk a little bit more about the process
of development so suppose you were a
blind or visually impaired developer
inside a company and you want to
communicate architecture how would you
use a UML diagram generally speaking UML
is not accessible at all and when I say
that what I mean is that oftentimes UML
is rendered in some way so you could do
it if you either had a graphical render
or some other approach
however oftentimes all UML really does
is provide you a sense of the structure
and there's lots of ways to navigate
structure so in other words if you're at
a design meeting and you put UML up on
the board yeah that's not gonna help but
if you have like a development tool
where you can navigate the classes and
read the code then that's a way that you
can be inclusive of a person that's
blind even if the rest of the team is
using UML at the same time so as long as
it's a textual and structural
representation you can represent class
diagrams but the visual version would be
very tricky pretty much now there was a
really cool dissertation done on it a
few years back I think the guy's name
was Alastair King and it's great work
but I don't think that there's really a
lot that's happened to make it
accessible besides one person's serious
dedicated effort yeah so that's
something if we're developing the fellow
person we want to be inclusive for
people that can see or can't see well we
just chew the news diagrams we should
keep - structural information that is in
the code base rather than auxiliary
documents yeah I mean and you know how
that stuff is anyway it kind of gets out
of date and whether yeah yeah I'm sure
there are also a few dissertations that
say well the UML diagrams they got
outdated super quickly right or have you
read that wonderful paper by a berry and
Petri do you know which what I'm talking
about
I think it's called UML in practice she
basically asked the question of do
people actually use UML and the answer
was pretty much not much yeah so I mean
yeah an AC paper I think it was an exit
figure that we link to that in the show
notes it's look very related to this
topic but it's a great paper yeah okay
so so far we've talked about
accessibility and tools websites and for
programming environments so I want to
talk a little bit about your work
because you have developed a programming
system that is inclusive of blind and
visually impaired children tell me more
so one of the observations that we made
right away was that although you could
do some work to make some of the tools
or ideas or development environments
accessible some of the barriers that we
saw students still having were with the
languages themselves and at the time
we made this sort of really innocent had
this sort of really innocent question
which was why do languages have that
design anyway and what was the evidence
for that decision so for example if you
have a for loop in a language it's
entirely reasonable that that might be
the case but why did they use the word
for and what was the evidence for that
choice because it wasn't just one person
that that impacted write like languages
are used by millions of people all over
the world so we might expect that you
could just hypothetically go to the
programming language design literature
look it up and figure out why they made
certain decisions and you were also
thinking about that case where you say a
for loop is pronounced as for open
bracket I that's addressed fracture very
normal here a bowl or all the bow if you
have to read it by spirit yeah exactly
so it wasn't so much that we thought
four is bad or some other word choices
it's just that we were sitting there
watching children like you know the 14
they barely know how to use the computer
they're just learning programming for
the first time and they're like for left
paren into AI and they're like I have no
idea what this is trying to tell me and
I just made it obvious to me like I
wonder what other words you could use
maybe we can look it up but when we
looked up information the literature
there wasn't any evidence of these
things so we decided let's get some
ourself so we started running like
surveys and we started writing them at
larger scale we started running
statistical experiments comparing
competing design choices for syntax and
amazing I'm sure it's not that
surprising but a lot of times you can
make stuff both orally more
understandable and more readable by
using common sense terminology and
getting rid of certain kinds of tokens
that you use the scientific method to
derive so for example a loop in quorum
is repeat ten times so that parameter in
a sense that then is in the middle of
keywords right which might be just
slightly unexpected for people that I
use to other programming languages
correct but there's also other options I
think there's repeat while and that
works just like a while loop but the key
though is that you need that word repeat
because that's a hint to a novice that
that's what that does semantically so
for example
the word repeat implies the concept of
iteration so when you look at the
statistics for how novices use those
tools if that words missing it's a
problem so one of the changes for
understanding correctly that you made
your program languages quorum is the
syntax has to be such that words
signifying meaning rather than being
weird words like for right and also a
lot of the punctuation has to be vetted
and the funny thing with those
punctuation results is that sometimes
there's sometimes they're kind of odd so
like for example this one surprised me
if you look at if statements and you
pull out the statistics for if
statements Java or many languages use
parentheses on the sides and it turns
out those are likely to get screwed up
however you you also get need to get rid
of the left brace but not the right one
which is sort of a bizarre decision
so in quorum you have an if and then you
have an expression and then the word end
so and it sounds sort of bizarre but if
you leave that left one in it turns out
that the statistical probability of
novice is getting that one correct are
pretty low so you pull it out and
everything is fine so instead of if open
brackets something something close
bracket you have if and then the
condition of and then ends right and
then the other weird decision but it
turns out to be pretty impactful is if
you test you you have this question of
should I use the double equal sign or a
single equals or a triple equals or
something like that and it turns out
that answer has a surprisingly large
effect size so for example if I use a
programming language like Java or Perl
or stuff like that and I compare I use a
double equal sign if I use a single
equal even if I use the same symbol for
assignment it increases the probability
of getting that token correct by eight
fold so it's way better to have let me
summarize that an equal sign for
assignments and also for comparison
oddly enough we've we in design test
cases where we use them both right next
to each other to try to trip offices up
because we were thinking if we're gonna
overload it that's got to fill up you up
turns out not and is this just for blind
kids or for all the kids everybody it
used to be in quorum that like we
we just started with blind children but
now I think it's something like 36
thousand kids a year ballpark so a lot
more than we would have expected so so
that world considerations for synthetics
how to make syntax more inclusive so
that if you read it it is easier to read
but also for other kids it's more
inclusive does your programming
environment also have IDE like features
to specifically support blind kids that
other ideas your programming tools don't
have yes so we've changed the various
features that we have for the blind over
time so but some of them include
additional navigation features that we
build into navigators and stuff like
that we have a self voicing option so
sort of funny because screen readers
sometimes break on certain platforms
which is stinky but reality one of the
things that we allow people to do in our
IDE is basically turn off the default
accessibility support and turn on just a
different speech engine which people
don't like as much however it works
everywhere and it's virtually guaranteed
to actually talk and that speech engine
is inside of your programming clever
pretty much yeah and it's not you know
so this is a thing oftentimes with
accessibility if you get to 80% and it
actually works it's enough so in our
case even though the tools that we had
weren't really perfect at the same time
it was enough to bring the number of
schools for the blind in the United
States that were teaching programming
from basically zero to about half that
is impressive so what are some features
that you consider to put into quorum but
didn't make the cut and for what reasons
Oh in terms of like language features or
IDE features or things that maybe if
we're programming we think oh this is a
good idea and you tried it and it didn't
work we want to hear about those okay
sure so if you we do a lot of
experiments because normally in Coram
week we call it evidence based and all
that really means is that before we
change the syntax and semantics of the
language and force every developer using
it or every kid using it to relearn it
we like we run a test and the test is
usually put people in a room how do
people try it or 50 people try it or a
hundred people try it and see what
happens
if it turns out people do pretty well
then it can go in the language and if it
turns out people
do very well then we kind of let it fall
by the wayside so we've tried a bunch of
these the one that's the most common
that has made it that is both in quorum
and has the strongest evidentiary
support for it is static typing it
sounds like a silly thing it's not like
forms the only language that has it but
the evidence is extremely clear that
static typing makes developers more
productive if you're using a dynamic
language what happens is as you go to
call a function oftentimes developers
don't know what to pass to the function
so they go hunting for it and it turns
out in experiments that amount of time
where they're off hunting for what to
pass to a dynamically type function
matches the time differences in the
studies which means basically
observational e we have evidence that
dynamic typing makes programmers slower
than static typing to us and this is for
sighted developers but I can imagine it
the effect might be even bigger for
blind developers because navigation is
such a big big issue because for us just
scrolling to the function is just that
just scrolling but if you're a blanket
or blind professional developer the
navigation is is so big of a hurdle it's
even worse I can imagine I've actually
never tested it with professional blind
developers but I would be very surprised
if you were wrong yeah I think you're
right so this is a nice example of
something that is useful for everyone
not just making it inclusive for what
developers but it's better for everyone
so it gets in the language yeah I think
so I think it goes both ways
oh there's there's one other that maybe
maybe your listeners will be interested
so the C++ standard a few years back
added lambdas to the specification and
we were curious whether or not that had
a positive or negative impact so we ran
an empirical study in just comparing C++
lambdas to iterators which is not the
only test you would need to make a
determination but it's starting point oh
it was also what apparently the spec
writers in the original white paper
claimed it was for its writers
apparently so we ran a test and we
compared freshmen in college
sophomores juniors seniors and then
professional developers that we
recruited from experts in lambdas and we
found that the experts had no
at all and it basically crushed all of
the novices so it's one of these weird
features where you know developers put
something in the language and maybe it
has a benefit but we found no evidence
to that this is interesting because
people will say oh I like it because as
it has lend us I mean I would say that I
show it sometimes as lembas but you're
saying if we measure if it helps it
doesn't help professionals and it hurts
kids and novices under the conditions of
the test that we read yes and I don't
think that lambdas versus iterators is
sort of the end of the story however we
did sort of just take it from what the
developers said and so it's a starting
point but it's possible there's other
weird situations where it might help
like event driven programming or
database or something but those need to
be verified through the scientific
method to see if that's actually true
yeah and I think you also mentioned
before not in the show but when we were
chatting before that lambdas are
specifically hard to be pronounced by
screenreader because the order is so
different from an iterator oh I don't
remember saying that but actually that
does make sense it's very plausible and
there's sort of a weird wacky syntax and
it has a wacky syntax yeah and sometimes
with that wacky syntax believe it or not
this is specially hard for blind
children screeners don't always read
literally so they skip characters Oh
what do they skip that it seems horrible
all sorts of stuff and when you think
about it that makes sense for like
Microsoft Word because you don't want to
reading every period that would drive
you insane oh yeah so basically what
some blind programmers do is they turn
on these verbosity modes to make sure
they hear everything but if you're blind
you're just starting out you don't even
know these things exist likely and if
you have to turn on reading every
character then it gets back to annoying
again so it's sort of like this
unfortunate sort of weird middle ground
with syntax where it's like you can do
it but it gets in the way
yeah because some programming language
have adults for list access and that
would be annoying if it would be skipped
I think so do you also take that into
account in the syntax of quorum so you
you are like oh let's not use dots
because screen readers could potentially
skip that Oh
comas actually no because we control the
speech pipelines separately we're very
judicious about what characters the
screen reader says because we
trol it yeah but I think you mentioned
before that sometimes they use quorum
with their brilliant screen reader and
then maybe yeah we cheat there too ok
you cheat yeah and your overrated
basically yeah although we don't
actually use dots to sort of one of the
weird quirky things about quorum syntax
that came from data but mildly annoys me
we found evidence that the dot operator
isn't the operator you should use for
objects for whatever reason surveys on
it at scale show the colon operator
makes more sense to human beings sort of
dry it drove me crazy enough that I ran
a replication study at a different
University in a different part of the
country just to try to prove it wrong
but unfortunately it replicated with
tremendous precision so you're saying we
should have used vaults for object
access oddly which everyone does yes
almost it's annoying
the wetlands Aaron Frank : no I've never
seen it in fact we kind of put it in
there as a junk character we didn't
think would win the study but you know I
don't get to choose these things
interesting yeah it's sort of bizarre
I'm not even exactly I have a guess but
I'm not entirely sure why we even
observe that result like for example
maybe dot just implies like the end of a
sentence or something or maybe colon
implies some kind of connected Lister's
I'm not really sure but you know we did
it we got the answer we replicated it
got the same answer everywhere else do
you do interesting ok but the fact that
tree readers read a character or or
don't read a character isn't what
influence the syntax everything you put
into quorum is there because you tried
it with people and you measured a
results not for everything when we first
started the project we were just working
with kids and so think about it like
this
the very first version of quorum we made
a bunch of decisions and not all of them
were evidence-based because that didn't
exist exactly and there was no such
thing as an evidence oriented language
that that did not exist so but we
thought we figured out really quickly
that we needed some evidence to make it
better so then what we did is every time
we made a change to the language we
started adjusting it over time but there
are a few decisions in quorum that are
left that we haven't run a study on yet
that I think will probably get
invalidated
one of them is we have this sort of
wacky multiple inheritance system it's
not like C++ is it's sort of it's this
own thing but it would not surprise me
of someday if we get a study together
that it could be invalidated but we try
to do that that's sort of our goal is to
sort as to run tests to invalidate our
own choices to make them better over
time so an interesting question there is
are there conflicts or tension between
the use for a programming language for
blind professional developers to use for
learning blind notices or sighted
novices or learning adult developers I
mean you say we tested it on people yeah
maybe some features are really great for
professional developers that shouldn't
be in the language for an offices I mean
isn't it a bit like that example you
gave with land us for experts they don't
matter but for kids they're really
matter so are you arguing for one
language that's perfect for everyone or
to Jew tailor a language that
specifically for blind novices and an
other language that has lambdas and all
the bells and whistles for professionals
what is best that I think that that's a
great question and I think that even the
academic community doesn't really know
and there's a really good reason it
turns out that between like the 50s
until about 2012 if you take a
reasonable chunk of the academic
literature in computer science on
programming languages they didn't
actually test with people so we don't
have a good sense no I say they didn't
test I mean almost overwhelmingly
universally did not test specifically
there's a scholar by the name of auntie
Johanna Kiana ho and he discovered that
during that period only about 22
controlled experiments were conducted
and the thing is that's just not enough
for us to really know now to be more to
have a more direct answer we do have
evidence like you say though that there
are some features that might be in
conflict between novices and
professionals one of them is again
static typing it turns out most of the
studies and replications that we've done
are somewhere in the ballpark of like
year 3 of an academic
up through like beginning professional
so we don't really have much good
information past that and we don't have
much good information about like
children or children with disabilities
or children with you know men women all
these different kinds of groups and I
think if we really want to flesh out
whether or not we can make languages
that find a good middle ground for
everybody we're gonna need a heck of a
lot more data from but not just for me
from like an entire academic community
otherwise we probably won't get there
yeah so in general would you say that
no just programming languages let's zoom
out a bit again so tools apps websites
and programming environments should they
have a specific version for the visually
impact and a special version for sighted
people like you have an English version
and a Spanish version and you could
imagine the same with novice programmers
should there be an office programming
experience and something developers use
or should it all be the same what is
your take on that specialize or
generalize my vote is for generalized
and you know I don't have a crystal ball
so I can't know for sure but here's my
reasoning when it comes to the first
question which is specialized for the
blind or not that one I would give a
hard no and the reason is because
sometimes when there's tools that are
developed just for the blind they don't
get maintained as well because you know
a company might make more money off the
one that's general-purpose than not so
that's one reason why at least I don't
know how it is working from but in the
United States well that's one reason why
they make laws about making general
technology accessible because they don't
want like Amazon to make like the the
blind reader that they maintained once
and then don't support for 50 years yeah
okay you but that is a practical
argument or maybe a capitalist argument
but it's not a philosophical argument as
it is now but the world every we would
like it to be do you think a specific
app for our website for the visually
impaired that maybe misses some features
that's how you developers we like is
that better or not suppose we have the
money to maintain whatever we want
okay that's a fair point I still think I
prefer the generalist though and the
reason is because a lot of the type of
stuff that I let's take an IDE that an
IDE
are things like buttons and lists and
trees and stuff those are actually
pretty accessible if it's there so I do
think that you can make specialized
features in ITES that would be
accessible that would be better though
so for example I do suspect you'd want
to specialize to bugger
because right now most debugging
technologies don't talk and there are
known - I've invented some talking to
voters over the years oh cool yeah
they're they're pretty fun they'll like
tell you like what variables are doing
and stuff like that they're pretty neat
the current version that we have the
tacking debugger is not great but I'm
hoping to build some new ones in the
some new projects I'm still curious
about that's looking the bugger how does
it work and why isn't it great yet but
what are you going to add there so it's
a little bit harder to build it on top
of like the JVM JavaScript and other
languages which is what quorum compiles
to a bunch of different places so during
my dissertation working like the
mid-2000s or so which makes me fold now
okay we we had like an interpreted
version of C that we were playing around
with and if you contract information
about the state of a program and a
little bit better way you can make
debuggers say all sorts of cool stuff
like say what kind of methods are being
called as you navigate instead of like
what line you're on say oh hey the
variable a was set to five and so you
can give people context about what's
changing in a program of course the
challenges are like what context you
give yeah it probably does so the stuff
that we did was relatively primitive we
would just kind of tell you the most
obvious thing like hey this method was
called or hey this variable changed but
nonetheless even with just those changes
these studies that we ran were pretty
obviously clear that it's better than
saying you're on line five you know
which is kind of obvious but nonetheless
like simple little things can sometimes
make a big difference for accessibility
but and they're just not enquire at this
point for technical reasons and all
because you don't believe they work well
is that called the butter yeah some they
kind of go in and out with every release
as we experiment so sometimes we are
building a new version so we'll pull
something out for a while and our
debugger right now is okay but it's
nothing super special so I can imagine
these type of features like a debugger
that talks aren't just you
so for visually impaired people but also
for sighted people can you give a few
examples of accessibility features in
general not just in ideas but also in
apps or websites that are designed for
visually impaired people but also can be
useful for sighted people I think I
might have already mentioned this one
but probably the most obvious and easy
to understand one is color contrast mode
yeah okay so a lot of the times the
features that people use with
accessibility can actually also be used
by people without disabilities and one
obvious one that'll that blind people
use heavily and so decided people is
keyboard shortcuts and think about it
some of them on some of the people that
I've known over the years that are blind
don't have a monitor or a mouse why
would they need it exactly and so like
you generally navigate like crazy with
the keyboard so if you're writing an app
and you make tons of awesome keyboard
shortcuts ways to navigate around of the
keyboard and you're an expert user
you'll probably like that anyway but by
people will love you forever
ah yeah so some features you make me you
might make then you might even make them
for expert users you're like oh yeah all
the shortcuts and then they're useful
for blind people but it also the other
way around yeah exactly or just make
them for you cuz like you might love
those things that have them extra and
then developers are crazy about keyboard
yeah that's the thing right including
myself so I'm also curious in the other
way around
are there accessibility features that
you can put into a tool or rupture your
app that might have her sighted people
that we sighted people would be like
why's that there that is confusing me
it's not helpful is that a thing or is
that not um yeah probably I mean the you
know it's really easy as a developer to
make a boo-boo and make something hard
to understand so a lot of the same
things like you know if your content is
written in a funny way or your interface
has weird color contrasts in it or the
buttons are aligned in the strange ways
or a good one might be tab order like
for a sighted person that's using the
keyboard shortcuts if they have weird
tab orders so that you're flying around
the interface in a funny way for a
sighted person that's gonna be odd you
know
imagine like a form where it jumps to
the wrong spots as you press tab right
yeah for you and I that because I'm a
sighted person - that would be really
annoying for a blind person who would
drive them bonkers yeah so it can be
accelerated by not being able to see it
yeah exactly
cool those are all things we can take
into account when making stuff for blind
people but also making it accessible for
other people that was everything I
wanted to ask is there anything you want
to add anything we missed
no I think the you has a lot of
questions that I I appreciate a whole
lot it made me actually think about it
to make her guest thing to make her
audience think we just want to ask you
one more thing if that's okay if we want
to read more about you your programming
language the cool stuff you're doing
what is your website why do we read more
about you well I'm taking google andreas
tefik and my university website is up
and I'll send you a link but if you want
to read more about forum you can go to
quorum language comm if you want to read
more about evidence there's a nice
little link right on the front and it'll
give you a bunch of little details about
how this evidence thing kind of works
cool we'll make sure all of those are in
the show notes
showing it cool thank you thanks for
being on the show thank you thanks for
listening to Nessie radio an educational
program brought to you by Triple E
software magazine for more about the
podcast including other episodes visit
our website at Etsy - radio net to
provide feedback you can comment on each
episode on the website or reach us on
LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or through our
slack channel at SC radio.com
you can also email us at team @ SC -
radio net this and all other episodes of
se radio is licensed under Creative
Commons license 2.5 thanks for listening